<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>wikichen</title>
    <description>Welcome to wikichen's playground on the web.</description>
    <link>http://wikichen.as</link>
    <atom:link href="http://wikichen.as/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Anus Tart</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a new start.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2013 03:40:34 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://wikichen.as/blogger/anustart/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://wikichen.as/blogger/anustart/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Forever Alone: Why Loneliness Matters in the Social Age</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I got up and went over and looked out the window. I felt so lonesome, all of a sudden. I almost wished I was dead. Boy, did I feel rotten. I felt so damn lonesome. I just didn’t want to hang around any more. It made me too sad and lonesome.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;— J.D. Salinger in &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/5107.The_Catcher_in_the_Rye&quot;&gt;Catcher in the Rye&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loneliness was a problem I experienced most poignantly in college. In the three years I spent at Carnegie Mellon, the crippling effects of loneliness slowly pecked away at my enthusiasm for learning and for life, until I was drowning in an endless depressive haze that never completely cleared until I left Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t for lack of trying either. At the warm behest of the orientation counselors, I joined just the right number of clubs, participated in most of the dorm activities, and tried to expand my social portfolio as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of it worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the extent that I sought out CAPS (our student psych and counseling service) for help, the platitudes they offered as advice (“Just put yourself out there!”) only served to confirm my suspicion that loneliness isn’t a very visible problem. (After all, the cure for loneliness isn’t exactly something that could be prescribed. “Have you considered transferring?” they finally suggested, after exhausting their list of thought-terminating clichés. I graduated early instead.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As prolonged loneliness took its toll, I became very unhappy—to put it lightly—and even in retrospect I have difficulty pinpointing a specific cause. It wasn’t that I didn’t know anyone or failed to make any friends, and it wasn’t that I was &lt;em&gt;alone&lt;/em&gt; more than I liked.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:def&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:def&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, I could point my finger at the abysmally fickle weather patterns of Pittsburgh, or the pseudo-suburban bubble that envelops the campus. There might even be a correlation between my academic dissonance with computer science and my feelings of loneliness. I might also just be an extremely unlikable person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For whatever the reason (or a confluence thereof) the reality remained that I struggled with loneliness throughout my time in college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recall a conversation with my friend Dev one particular evening on the patio of our dormitory. It was the beginning of my junior and last year at CMU, and I had just finished throwing an ice cream party for the residents I oversaw as an RA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Glad to be back?” he asked as he plopped down on a lawn chair beside me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No, not really.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sun was setting, and any good feelings about the upcoming semester with it. We made small talk about the school in general, as he had recently transferred, but eventually Dev asked me if I was happy there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No, not really.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Why do you think you’re so miserable here?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I don’t know. A lot of things, I guess. But mostly because I feel lonely. Like I don’t belong, like I can’t relate to or connect with anyone on an emotional level. I haven’t made any quality relationships here that I would look back on with any fond memories. Fuck… I don’t know what to do.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;College, at least for me, was a harrowing exercise in how helplessly debilitating, hopelessly soul-crushing, and at times life-threatening loneliness could be. It’s a problem nobody talks about, and it’s been a subject of much personal relevance and interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;loneliness-as-a-health-problem&quot;&gt;Loneliness as a Health Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent article published on Slate &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slate.com/articles/health_and_science/medical_examiner/2013/08/dangers_of_loneliness_social_isolation_is_deadlier_than_obesity.html&quot;&gt;outlines the hidden dangers of social isolation&lt;/a&gt;. Chronic loneliness, as Jessica Olien discovered, poses serious health risks that not only impact mental health but physiological well-being as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lack of quality social relationships in a person’s life &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.plosmedicine.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pmed.1000316&quot;&gt;has been linked to an increased mortality risk&lt;/a&gt; comparable to smoking and alcohol consumption and exceeds the influence of other risk factors like physical inactivity and obesity. It’s hard to brush off loneliness as a character flaw or an ephemeral feeling when you realize it kills more people than obesity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research also shows that loneliness &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20652462&quot;&gt;diminishes sleep quality and impairs physiological function&lt;/a&gt;, in some cases reducing immune function and boosting inflammation, which &lt;a href=&quot;http://researchnews.osu.edu/archive/lonely.htm&quot;&gt;increases risk for diabetes and heart disease&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why hasn’t loneliness gotten much attention as a medical problem? Olien shares the following observation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As a culture we obsess over strategies to prevent obesity. We provide resources to help people quit smoking. But I have never had a doctor ask me how much meaningful social interaction I am getting. Even if a doctor did ask, it is not as though there is a prescription for meaningful social interaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a society we look down upon those who admit to being lonely, we cast and ostracize them with labels like “loners” insofar as they prefer to hide behind shame and doubt rather than speak up. This dynamic only makes it harder to devise solutions to what is clearly a larger societal issue, and it certainly brings to question the effects of culture on our perception of loneliness as a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;loneliness-as-a-culture-problem&quot;&gt;Loneliness as a Culture Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen Fry, in a blog post titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stephenfry.com/2013/06/24/only-the-lonely/&quot;&gt;Only the Lonely&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; which explains his suicide attempt last year, describes in detail his struggle with depression. His account offers a rare and candid glimpse into the reality of loneliness with which those afflicted often hide from the public:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Lonely? I get invitation cards through the post almost every day. I shall be in the Royal Box at Wimbledon and I have serious and generous offers from friends asking me to join them in the South of France, Italy, Sicily, South Africa, British Columbia and America this summer. I have two months to start a book before I go off to Broadway for a run of Twelfth Night there.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I can read back that last sentence and see that, bipolar or not, if I’m under treatment and not actually depressed, what the fuck right do I have to be lonely, unhappy or forlorn? I don’t have the right. But there again I don’t have the right not to have those feelings. Feelings are not something to which one does or does not have rights.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;In the end loneliness is the most terrible and contradictory of my problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United States, approximately 60 million people, or 20% of the population, feel lonely. According to the &lt;em&gt;General Social Survey&lt;/em&gt;, between 1985 and 2004, the number of people with whom the average American discusses important matters &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thelonelyamerican.com/&quot;&gt;decreased from three to two&lt;/a&gt;, and the number with no one to discuss important matters with tripled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modernization has been cited as &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loneliness#Frequency&quot;&gt;a reason for the intensification&lt;/a&gt; of loneliness in every society around the world, attributed to greater migration, smaller household sizes, and a larger degree of media consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Japan, loneliness is an even more pervasive, layered problem mired in cultural parochialisms. Gideon Lewis-Kraus pens &lt;a href=&quot;http://harpers.org/archive/2013/08/sleeping-together/&quot;&gt;a beautiful narrative on Harper’s&lt;/a&gt; in which he describes his foray into the world of Japanese co-sleeping cafés:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Why do you think he came here, to the sleeping café?”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“He wanted five-second hug maybe because he had no one to hug. Japan is &lt;em&gt;haji&lt;/em&gt; culture. Shame. Is shame culture. Or maybe also is shyness. I don’t know why. Tokyo people . . . very alone. And he does not have . . . ” She thought for a second, shrugged, reached for her phone. “Please hold moment.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;She held it close to her face, multitouched the screen not with thumb and forefinger but with tiny forefinger and middle finger. I could hear another customer whispering in Japanese in the silk-walled cubicle at our feet. His co-sleeper laughed loudly, then laughed softly. Yukiko tapped a button and shone the phone at my face. The screen said COURAGE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took an enormous effort for me to come to terms with my losing battle with loneliness and the ensuing depression at CMU, and an even greater leap of faith to reach out for help. (That it was to no avail is another story altogether.) But what is even more disconcerting to me is that the general stigma against loneliness and mental health issues, hinging on &lt;a href=&quot;http://thetartan.org/2012/12/3/forum/mentalhealth&quot;&gt;an unhealthy stress culture&lt;/a&gt;, makes it hard for afflicted students to seek assistance at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Olien puts it, “In a society that judges you based on how expansive your social networks appear, loneliness is difficult to fess up to. It feels shameful.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To truly combat loneliness from a cultural angle, we need to start by examining our own fears about being alone and to recognize that as humans, loneliness is often symptomatic of our &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maslow&#39;s_hierarchy_of_needs&quot;&gt;unfulfilled social needs&lt;/a&gt;. Most importantly, we need to accept that it’s okay to feel lonely. Fry, signing off on his heartfelt post, offers this insight:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Loneliness is not much written about (my spell-check wanted me to say that loveliness is not much written about—how wrong &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; is) but humankind is a social species and maybe it’s something we should think about more than we do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;loneliness-as-a-technology-problem&quot;&gt;Loneliness as a Technology Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology, and by extension media consumption in the Internet age, adds the most perplexing (and perhaps the most interesting) dimension to the loneliness problem. As it turns out, technology isn’t necessarily helping us feel more connected; in some cases, it makes loneliness worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount of time you spend on Facebook, as a recent study found, is inversely related to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.plosone.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0069841&quot;&gt;how happy you&lt;/a&gt; feel throughout the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a moment to watch this video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe src=&quot;http://player.vimeo.com/video/70534716&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;281&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a powerful, sombering reminder that our growing dependence on technology to communicate has serious social repercussions, to which Cohen presents his central thesis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are lonely, but we’re afraid of intimacy, while the social networks offer us three gratifying fantasies:
1) That we can put our attention wherever we want it to be.
2) That we will always be heard.
3) That we will never have to be alone.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;And that third idea, that we will never have to be alone, is central to changing our psyches. It’s shaping a new way of being. The best way to describe it is:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I share, therefore I am.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public discourse on the cultural ramifications of technology is certainly not a recent development, and the general sentiment that our perverse obsession with sharing will be humanity’s downfall continues to echo in various forms around the web: articles proclaiming that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fastcompany.com/3013197/unplug/how-instagram-almost-ruined-my-life&quot;&gt;Instagram is ruining people’s lives&lt;/a&gt;, the existence of a section on Reddit called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reddit.com/r/cringepics&quot;&gt;cringepics&lt;/a&gt; where people congregate to ridicule things others post on the Internet, the increasing number of self-proclaimed “&lt;a href=&quot;http://adage.com/article/digitalnext/181-000-social-media-gurus-ninjas-masters-mavens-twitter/239026/&quot;&gt;social media gurus&lt;/a&gt;” on Twitter, to name a few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The signs seem to suggest we have reached a tipping point for “social” media that’s not very social on a personal level, but whether it means a catastrophic implosion or a gradual return to more authentic forms of interpersonal communications remains to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While technology has been a source of social isolation for many, it has the capacity to alleviate loneliness as well. A study funded by the online dating site eHarmony shows that couples who met online are less likely to divorce and &lt;a href=&quot;http://healthland.time.com/2013/06/03/more-satisfaction-less-divorce-for-people-who-meet-spouses-online/&quot;&gt;achieve more marital satisfaction&lt;/a&gt; than those who met in real life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same model could potentially be applied to friendships, and it’s frustrating to see that there aren’t more startups leveraging this opportunity when the problem  is so immediate and in need of solutions. It’s a matter of exposure and education on the truths of loneliness, and unfortunately we’re just not there yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The perils of loneliness shouldn’t be overlooked in an increasingly hyperconnected world that often tells another story through rose-tinted lenses. Rather, the gravity of loneliness should be addressed and brought to light as a multifaceted problem, one often muted and stigmatized in our society. I learned firsthand how painfully real of a problem loneliness could be, and more should be done to spread its awareness and to help those affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What do you think I should do?” I looked at Dev as the last traces of sunlight teetered over the top of Morewood Gardens. It was a rhetorical question—things weren’t about to get better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Find better people,” he replied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I offered him a weak smile in return, but little did I know then how prescient those words were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the year that followed, I started a fraternity with some of the best kids I’d come to know (Dev included), graduated college and moved to San Francisco, made some of the best friends I’ve ever had, and never looked back, if only to remember, and remember well, that it’s never easy being lonely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:def&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It should be noted that there is a clear distinction between feeling lonely, which is a subjective experience, and being solitary, which is simply a lack of contact with people. For the purpose of this discussion, I’m referring to the former and the former only.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:def&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://wikichen.as/blogger/forever-alone/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://wikichen.as/blogger/forever-alone/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lessons Learned Writing, Part I</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of August I started a project to &lt;a href=&quot;/write-like-a-motherfucker/&quot;&gt;write everyday for a year&lt;/a&gt;. 2 weeks, 17 posts, 13k words, 50k views, and a lot of caffeine later, I’m happy to be writing this update to share what I’ve learned and to propose some appropriate changes to the scope of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;writing-is-scary-and-hard-but-do-it-anyway&quot;&gt;Writing is scary and hard. But do it anyway.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of people messaged me expressing interest in what I’m doing. &lt;em&gt;I want to write, and I wish I had time and the guts to put everything out there&lt;/em&gt;, they said. That’s a nice bullshit excuse you’ve got there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/pageviews.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Page Views&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t start writing because I thought I was good enough. Hell, I still think most of what I write is complete and utter horseshit. But so what? Your writing will never get better if you don’t write. I decided to write with complete transparency because it keeps me accountable to my peers and the world at large. I make sure people read what I write, so I can get better at writing and have no excuse when I don’t produce—&lt;em&gt;shit, people actually read my stuff, better make sure to write more&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Write for yourself, write what you care about. Writing frequently helps make the actual products of writing less personal, and it helps to take things less personally because there will be days when your posts are bad and either nobody reads them or everyone hates them. Which brings us to my next point: making people care about what you write.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nobody-will-care-unless-you-make-the-effort-to-share&quot;&gt;Nobody will care unless you make the effort to share.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It pisses me off to see &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/writers-on-writing/f7dfa4c0625a&quot;&gt;self-serving posts like this&lt;/a&gt; on Medium in which the author argues that a curated publishing platform is where nobodies like himself truly belong. I’m sorry, but the reason why nobody reads your crap is because you don’t care enough to do the hard work after you’re done writing. It promotes a lazy attitude of publishing, whereby the author simply sits around after he’s hit the Submit button and expects thousands of readers to just flock to his elegantly crafted post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open your eyes, because I’ll have you know that &lt;em&gt;the entire Internet&lt;/em&gt; is for nobodies like us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a nobody. I have fewer followers and friends on social networks than what Justin Bieber’s accounts eat for breakfast. Yet I still manage to help people find and read the stuff I write, because I care to make the effort to share—I want my writing out there for the world to read and judge and share. It’s hard to make people care when you don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/reddit_submissions.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reddit Submissions&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For starters, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reddit.com/&quot;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt; is a fantastic place to share your writing. There are hundreds upon hundreds of subreddits catering to every niche subject you can think of. There’s a subreddit for everything, so you really have no excuse. It’s also a great place to get feedback: if your post gets upvoted, there must be something people liked that you could take away for your next post, and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my post on &lt;a href=&quot;/the-tao-of-pooh/&quot;&gt;The Tao of Pooh&lt;/a&gt; hit the front page of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reddit.com/r/books&quot;&gt;r/books&lt;/a&gt;, it sent more than 40,000 hits to my site. Other posts didn’t do so well. Like I said, you win some days, you lose some days. Keep writing and carry on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;writing-has-become-one-of-my-most-rewarding-creative-feedback-loops&quot;&gt;Writing has become one of my most rewarding creative feedback loops.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most surprising benefit I found in writing with a schedule is how much it challenges and pushes my creative side. Publishing on a regular basis gives my day-to-day life some semblance of progress. It also helps frame my days under a narrative lens that seek to derive meaning from otherwise mundane observations about life and my interests. I’m learning more about myself as I write, and this feedback loop has become a positive driving force in my self-expression and creative identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing has also led me to connect with people I wouldn’t have otherwise had the opportunity to interact with, and I’m always pleasantly surprised when people reach out to me to express their own sentiments or spur their own discussions regarding my writing. It’s one of the most rewarding feelings I’ve ever experienced doing anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To that end, I want to make some changes to the project. &lt;span class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;Instead of writing everyday, I’m going to publish a longer post every Monday, Wednesday, and Friday.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The daily constraint really puts pressure on shipping content that may not be all that interesting or substantive. The off days will be much needed time to flesh out my ideas, and the decreased posting frequency will allow me to develop meatier pieces that are more engaging and informative. Part of this is because I discovered many of my posts are media heavy, and processing images really cut into my allocated writing time, even though they’re just as relevant and important to the content of the posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also underestimated how much development time this blog needs. On the weekends, rather than write, I want to instead use that time to make improvements to the design and functionality of the blog. Good design can make better reading experiences, and as a designer with a vested interest in web publishing, this is the perfect medium on which to experiment and play with elements like typography, responsive layouts, flexible grids, and creative storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, it really makes my day when I know that people are taking the time to read my writing, so I want to say thanks to all the friends and strangers alike who have read, shared, or given me feedback on my posts. You’re a large part of why I continue to write, and your support means everything to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for much more.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://wikichen.as/blogger/lessons-learned-writing-part-1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://wikichen.as/blogger/lessons-learned-writing-part-1/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Beyond Mordor: The Power of Completionism</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was originally published on Medium, which never saw many views. I hope it finds a new audience here, as it explores two of my favorite things: video games and user-centered design.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It didn’t seem long ago that my brother and I were excitedly fantasizing about a potential Lego game by Traveller’s Tales set in J. R. R. Tolkien’s epic Middle Earth as we smashed and built our way through their &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lego_Star_Wars:_The_Video_Game&quot;&gt;original brickified Star Wars games&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t had the pleasure of playing any of the Lego video games, here’s how Traveller’s Tales’ tried-and-true formula works: license a Lego product line based on a successful, mass market movie and/or book franchise, design levels around the main events of the story, turn the environment and characters into plastic bricks, sprinkle a ton of collectibles for replayability and a dash of kid-friendly humor, add easy drop-in/drop-out cooperative play, and voila, you have a fun, addicting game that seems to capture the essence of its source material generally better than its more true-to-life counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My brother and I have played just about every Lego game since the inception of the franchise seven odd years ago, so imagine our giddy delight when we found out Traveller’s Tales brought the newest &lt;a href=&quot;http://thelordoftherings.lego.com/&quot;&gt;The Lord of the Rings Lego sets&lt;/a&gt; into digital life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as gameplay is concerned, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.metacritic.com/game/xbox-360/lego-the-lord-of-the-rings&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lego The Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; follows the franchise recipe down to the letter. What stood out to me, and perhaps what made this entry such a compelling case study of game design, is the sheer amount of additional content Traveller’s Tales put into the game that sets it apart from its predecessors, for better or worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/legolotr_screenshot.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Lego LotR&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a seemingly endless amount of things to collect in Lego Middle Earth: Mithril bricks to find for crafting tools, characters to meet and do fetch quests for, treasures to unearth, and Lego studs for currency. That Middle Earth is rendered as an open world (instead of a much smaller hub in the previous games) is a testament to the time and effort it takes to obtain 100% completion of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game, in its mad attempt to be crowned the Witch-king of collectibles, awakened some latent obsessive-compulsive tendencies that ultimately drove me to achieve that 100% status. Towards the end, I wasn’t playing for fun anymore. I played for completion, for a sense of closure a number would bring, knowing I have done and conquered everything the game had to offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;completionism-in-practice&quot;&gt;Completionism in Practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see completionism at work in contexts surrounding us and in a lot of the things we do. The human need for completion and closure is best explained by the New Yorker article &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/elements/2013/04/why-we-need-answers.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why We Need Answers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When we can’t immediately gratify our desire to know, we become highly motivated to reach a concrete explanation. That motivation…lies at the heart of most other common motives: achievement, affiliation, power, and the like. We want to eliminate the distress of the unknown. We want, in other words, to achieve “cognitive closure.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relating to cognitive science, Gestalt psychology states under the Law of Closure that the human mind attempts to fill in gaps wherever incompleteness is present, that is, we instinctively strive to reach a state of closure when things are incomplete. Humans have a deep-rooted psychological drive to finish tasks, known as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.psychwiki.com/wiki/Zeigarnik_Effect&quot;&gt;Zeigarnik effect&lt;/a&gt;, which observes that people remember uncompleted tasks better than completed ones. In my case, the incompleted state of the &lt;em&gt;Lego LotR&lt;/em&gt; game created tension, improving cognitive accessibility to the task-relevant details (or more specifically, an obsessive need for its completion).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the design world, a recent trend in web usability is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ui-patterns.com/patterns/CompletenessMeter&quot;&gt;completeness meter&lt;/a&gt;, a feature usually implemented on sites to encourage users to fill in profile fields or perform certain tasks. The meter tracks the progress of the user towards a completion rate, drawing on psychological factors like feedback loop and positive reinforcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/completeness_meter.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Examples of the Completeness Meter&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The emergence of these “gamified” techniques tapping into completionism warrants some scrutiny, because as my time with &lt;em&gt;Lego LotR&lt;/em&gt; showed, this completionist-driven behavior may not be all roses and toy bricks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-good-and-evil-of-completionism&quot;&gt;The Good and Evil of Completionism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;em&gt;Lego LotR&lt;/em&gt; shows, capitalizing on our inherent need for completion can capture the player’s attention and help them derive more enjoyment and value from the game, but to an extent. In an ideal scenario, everyone wins; the developer creates a better game and the user enjoys a better game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The completeness meter is a great UX tool that takes advantage of completionism to better the product experience for both the developer and the user. It helps guide the user through the interface and track their progression through the site, offering feedback on how they can improve their utility of the service. At the same time, the increased engagement and self-directed activity benefit the developers, allowing them to learn more about their users and iterate on the product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it’s worth thinking about the context in which completionism may be detrimental to the user experience. In my time with &lt;em&gt;Lego LotR&lt;/em&gt;, my behavior devolved from playing for fun and engagement into a rather pointless binge for completion. It added nothing to my enjoyment of the game and, to a degree, tainted my impression of its quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When designing to bring about completionistic tendencies, it’s also important to think about the type of users who would actually be turned off by a persistent reminder of their lack of progress. I often find myself annoyed at having to close the panels on Google+ reminding me to fill in my profile information when I have no desire to do so. Not everyone has the same attitude towards completionism, so tread carefully when introducing these mechanics to different users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What made &lt;em&gt;Lego LotR&lt;/em&gt; so addicting—tapping on gamers’ tendencies to do everything to extend replayability of the interactive experience—is not new in game design, but the implications of replicating this completionist behavior elsewhere, such as in web usability, pose an interesting use case for product designers to better serve the needs of users and the product when implemented properly and responsibly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://wikichen.as/designer/beyond-mordor-the-power-of-completionism/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://wikichen.as/designer/beyond-mordor-the-power-of-completionism/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Live Slowly</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;An old friend taught me a valuable lesson about life one Friday afternoon at a brunch spot in Tainan, Taiwan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Live slowly&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I waited, with equal parts anticipation and nervousness, under the collective shade of some trees outside the gated entrance of an all female high school in Tainan. We had agreed to meet here, but with sweat steadily running down my back under an unforgiving midday sun I wondered why I didn’t think to suggest somewhere indoors, and preferably air conditioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A white sedan turned the corner and made its way to the gates. A girl small in stature, sporting a black top and a navy blue skirt, stepped out of the car, and with one sweeping motion shut its doors, threw a quick wave and a radiant smile in my direction, and strode swiftly across the street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hi, it’s been a long time,” I blurted out as I went in for a hug. There was a slightly hesitant, awkward vibe, but then again, we haven’t seen each other in seven years, and it’s been twice that time since we’ve talked or spent time together with any substance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Come on, let’s go check out this great brunch place I found nearby,” she gestured for me to follow her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made our way through a few alleyways, occasionally making the odd turn, until a two-story building, whose recent renovations were made evident by a paint job too fresh and some questionable gate installments, came into view; it was sitauted next to a plot of unused land that looked like someone’s neglected garden project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entrance to the brunch shop was tucked behind a tall stone partition shielding it from the streets, with a meticulously adorned stone path leading to its doorstep. The wind chimes perched on top of the glass doors rattled as we entered the tiny store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside, an employee greeted and directed us to the seating area on the second floor. The stone steps leading upstairs were steeper than the ones I was accustomed to back home—&lt;em&gt;thanks, Obama!&lt;/em&gt;—and I almost tripped on my way up. But I survived, and soon we were surrounded by low wooden desks and chairs; the atmosphere was reminiscent of a casual, folksy teahouse, if you’ve ever been to one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I love old buildings like this,” my friend said as she drew one of the wooden chairs next to the windows and sat down. “They don’t really build them like this anymore.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After much deliberation, we both ordered a set meal that was more Western in influence than I expected—scrambled eggs, sausages, toast, and the likes—and made some small talk, or as much casual dialogue as one could muster to someone with whom you lost contact since fifth grade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So what are we doing after? How long are we going to be here?” I asked as we cleaned up our plates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I don’t know. Let’s just sit here.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Till when?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Till you’re happy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Wait, so you just sit here until you’re done?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yeah, exactly. Sometimes with friends, sometimes by myself. We Tainan people call this &lt;em&gt;slow living&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She went on to explain that she loves coming home to Tainan because she found the pace in Taipei, where she studies, to be too demanding, too hectic, for her to appreciate the nuances of everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Kind of like New York City,” I pointed out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yeah, you can say that. In Tainan, people stop to smell the roses, to drink afternoon tea and to relish time spent in the company of others. It’s sad how we kind of lost that way of living in other parts of the world.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we sat there continuing our conversation, at times marked by quiet yet welcoming pauses, I started embracing the message she was trying to convey, about living life more slowly. There’s a peace in the mundane and the silence and the immediacy of the moment that brings about questions I never thought to ask myself, having always been caught up in the hustle and bustle of modern life. I stopped making time to take life more slowly, to see things more clearly, to spend time more casually. I stopped living at the cost of my happiness. Why do I always need to be going somewhere? Why do I always need to be doing something? Why is it that I never slow down every once in a while to enjoy my life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realized that everything she had us do that day—our rendezvous at a deserted high school and the long walk to the idyllic brunch spot that stands as a nostalgic remnant of a slower time—was a lesson in practice. In an afternoon, she taught me how to live slowly, to live better. And in a way, I wrote this as a reflection of that very lesson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Come on, let’s go for a walk,” she said as she grabbed her bag. I furrowed my brows, though more out of curiosity than concern, and followed her out the door.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a day better lived slowly, and it was a good day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://wikichen.as/blogger/live-slowly/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://wikichen.as/blogger/live-slowly/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Taiwan: A Sensory Experience</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A trip to Taiwan is a full-on assault on your senses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stepping out into the open air, your skin immediately becomes clammy with the intense humidity. It’s unpleasant, almost suffocating, and in less than half an hour you will be drenched in your own perspiration. You wonder how anyone gets anything done here, but somehow life goes on and the people carry on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are scooters everywhere—on the road and parked in front of stores, spilling onto the streets. You notice that the streets are narrow, the buildings so tightly packed there is barely any space, if any, separating them. And the signs, they’re everywhere, stacked on top and beside each other, jutting out of the walls of buildings like weeds unchecked and growing out of control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life in the city is a noisy, busy existence. Fleets of scooters and mopeds deafen the streets with their droning engines, and the constant flow of automobile and foot traffic alike make the streets seem smaller than they already are. There are people everywhere, signaling a vibrant sign of life, but maybe too much so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the stores open out into the streets. In a single block you spot no less than a dozen restaurants and food stands, mixed with an assorted array of local businesses ranging from health clinics and bike shops to electronic stores and name brand clothing stores. In every direction this arrangement repeats itself. Wait, is that a 7-Eleven not even half a block from another 7-Eleven? You’ll see another dozen before venturing out of the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At night, the labyrinthic grid of streets are brilliantly lit by the high hanging signs of their stores, creating a dazzling effect as if you were transported to an alternate neon wonderland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a beautiful, scenic side to Taiwan as well. The mountains and the beaches and the lakes offer incomprable refuge for those seeking respite from the hustle and bustle of urban life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taiwan is an island with a culture heavily influenced by the Chinese ghosts of its past and the forces of globalization from the West. It struggles with an identity split between preserving traditions while embracing modernity in the 21st century. But perhaps more importantly, it’s a place with fantastic foods, natural views, friendly people, and a palpable sense of cultural pride with an eye towards the future. It’s a place I called home for more than twelve years, and I can’t recommend it enough for those who travel to expand their horizons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- add taiwan_temple.jpg --&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/taiwan-alley.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/taiwan-buildings.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/taiwan-family.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/taiwan-mountains.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/taiwan-night.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/taiwan-noparking.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/taiwan-policestation.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/taiwan-sunmoonlake.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://wikichen.as/blogger/taiwan-a-sensory-experience/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://wikichen.as/blogger/taiwan-a-sensory-experience/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Photowalking Through a Taiwanese Night Market</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’ve long believed that good food, good eating, is all about risk. Whether we’re talking about unpasteurized Stilton, raw oysters or working for organized crime ‘associates,’ food, for me, has always been an adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;— Anthony Bourdain in &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/33313.Kitchen_Confidential&quot;&gt;Kitchen Confidential&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there’s a definitive activity you should do while visiting Taiwan, it’s to set aside an evening to experience the sights, sounds, and smells of a Taiwanese night market. With over one hundred night markets in Taiwan, these ephemeral street markets of the late evenings offer some of the most authentic cultural impressions and local foods (we call these roadside dishes xiaochi 小吃, which roughly translates to snacks or fast food) you’ll find on this side of Asia. Let’s take a walk through a typical night market (this particular one is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://foursquare.com/v/%E8%8A%B1%E5%9C%92%E5%A4%9C%E5%B8%82/4bb860e153649c74b6fb46fb&quot;&gt;Huayuan Night Market&lt;/a&gt; 花園夜市, located in Tainan).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row-fluid row-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;span6&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/market-arcade.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;span6&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/market-shops.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing you’ll notice is that it really does feel like a market: crowded and noisy, as if all the chaotic elements of the universe decided to descend upon this small congested plot of bedazzled land on this fateful night of your visit. You’ll have a hard time wading through the sea of eager, hungry patrons, whose foot traffic is reduced to the narrow walkways between rows of makeshift stands, while your head busily tries to discern the cacophony of smells flooding your nostrils. It’s all a bit too overwhelming, but that’s the essential charm of the night market—ordered chaos in the midst of bewildering unknowns. Learn to embrace it, and try not to get lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row-fluid row-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;span6&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/market-kebobs.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;span6&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/market-squid.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll find all sorts of interesting edible things here. No, stop making that face, get a grip. There are skewers of every variety: beef, lamb, fish balls, congealed pig blood, squid, and so much more. Squid on a stick is a staple at night markets. Stop squirming—this is some next level delicious seafood shit &lt;em&gt;on a stick&lt;/em&gt;. Try one, I promise it tastes better than it looks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row-fluid row-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;span6&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/market-sides.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;span6&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/market-meats.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t even begin to fathom all of the small delicacies they sell: octopus parts, banded seaweed, soy bean curds, duck innards, various pickled vegetables, marinated meats of every color and spice, to name a few. If you’re vegetarian, you’re going to have a bad time. Otherwise, go crazy like I usually do—sample everything, because most of this stuff is beyond tasty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row-fluid row-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;span6&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/market-oysternoodles.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;span6&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/market-oysterpancake.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oysters are a big part of the Taiwanese night market palette, and they go especially well in a couple of signature dishes: oyster vermicelli (蚵仔麵線) and oyster omelette (蚵仔煎). The vermicelli dish is a noodle soup with a sticky, gooey base derived from the caramelized sugars of the vermicelli dough, while the omelette is a favorite dish among foreigners comprising potato starch and egg batter as the wrap, topped off with a savory sauce—the result is a chewy, sweet mouthfeel that is out of this world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row-fluid row-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;span6&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/market-tofu.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;span6&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/market-sausages.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another classic night market eat is the stinky tofu (臭豆腐). It smells like ass to those unfamiliar, and you can usually tell from a mile away. The odor is attributed to the fermentation of the tofu, which is then deep fried and served with chili sauce. The authentic stands would include a side of sweet and sour pickled cabbage, which helps alleviate the greasiness of the tofu. It’s a unique Taiwanese dish not for the faint of heart, but those who smell past its stench are privy to enjoy what I deem to be a hidden gastronomic treasure of Taiwan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row-fluid row-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;span6&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/market-candies.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;span6&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/market-mochi.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the sweets and desserts are full of endless variety and delight. The sheer amount of stuff available (that’s actually palatable to those who would rather keep diabetes away) puts any American candy store to shame. In the mood for something sweet and savory? We have mochi treats, plus you can dip it in a bunch of awesome flavors: green tea, red bean, sesame, you name it. Just writing about them makes my mouth water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Night markets are one of my favorite facets of Taiwanese culture. They imbue all the great things about my people: the rowdy, happy-go-lucky crowds, the dazzling colors of tradition, the myriad culinary surprises that captivate those more adventurously inclined. If you want to experience Asian culture at its best, start here.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://wikichen.as/foodie/photowalking-through-a-taiwanese-night-market/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://wikichen.as/foodie/photowalking-through-a-taiwanese-night-market/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why 7-Eleven is Everywhere in Asia</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever found yourself in an urban part of Asia, chances are you’ll come across 7-Eleven stores nearly everywhere you go. The ubiquity of these chain convenience stores on street corners has been a subject of much personal curiosity since I was a kid growing up in Taiwan, so I’m actually going to set aside some time today to lay down some groundwork on answering this seemingly trite inquiry: just why are there so many 7-Elevens in Asia compared to the rest of the world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walk into any 7-Eleven store in Taiwan and you’re immediately hit with sensory overload. The blast of cool air from the store’s AC hits your face at the same time as the distinctive smell: a mix of tea leaf eggs and assorted eats from the hotpot section of the store and that unique 7-Eleven store fragrance reeking of packaged foods. Your eyes try to make sense of the shelves upon shelves of items you’ll never have time to browse one by one. The layouts of these 7-Eleven stores are near identical: clean and organized, minimally structured to showcase the goods. Some have even begun to add a table counter with stools for your more leisurely morning trips to the store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/7-eleven_snacks.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;7-Eleven Snacks&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new 7-Eleven opens every two hours somewhere in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stores are so ubiquitous in Taiwan that the Taiwanese government &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wantchinatimes.com/news-subclass-cnt.aspx?id=20110610000116&amp;amp;cid=1103&quot;&gt;collaborated with 7-Eleven&lt;/a&gt; to provide the public with free health checkups. It’s not uncommon to come across intersections in Taipei where &lt;a href=&quot;http://articles.chicagotribune.com/2007-08-05/news/0708040400_1_all-night-convenience-mainland-affairs-council-night-markets&quot;&gt;two or three 7-Eleven stores stand across from each other&lt;/a&gt;. With a population of about 23 million and over 4,830 stores, Taiwan has the highest per capita number of these 24/7 outlets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are more 7-Eleven licensed stores than McDonald’s at more than 50,000. Spanning 16 countries, the largest market is actually Japan, where close to 30% of all 7-Eleven outlets are located (around 15,000) and where, quite appropriately, 7-Eleven’s worldwide operations are headquartered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/7-eleven_hotpot.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;7-Eleven Hot Pot Food&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The company was founded in 1927 in Dallas, Texas, operating convenience stores in various parts of the United States then called “Tot’em Stores” because customers would “tote” away their purchased goods. It was only after WWII that the name was changed to 7-Eleven. Through a tumultous history rife with financial challenges, 7-Eleven and its parent holding company Southland Corporation was rescued in 1998 from bankrupty by its largest franchisee, a japanese company called Ito-Yokado, which later became what is now known as Seven &amp;amp; I Holdings Co., who acquired 7-Eleven as its subsidiary in 2005.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporate history partly explains 7-Eleven’s tremendous market penetration in Asia, but their success can also be largely attributed to an ingenious business model and franchise format capitalizing on the value of convenience. It’s capitalistic consumerism writ large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost all 7-Elevens in the world, be it the United States or Japan, are operated by franchisees, who are encouraged to tailor their outlets to the local demographics and tastes. Torsten Stocker, a China-based partner at strategy consulting firm Monitor Group, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/05/24/7-eleven-expansion_n_1543277.html&quot;&gt;praises the forward-thinking business model&lt;/a&gt; under the guise of an unconventional localization strategy. “[7-Eleven] has local partners who understand the environment in their market very well,” he stated in an email. “This allows them to grow very rapidly and at much lower investment.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/7-eleven_cold.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;7-Eleven Cold Section&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help its franchisees align with the brand, 7-Eleven sends out consultants twice a week, who are issued a propietary data-analysis tool called the Retail Information System that allows store owners to track what products are selling in real time. Introduced in Japan, the RIS allows 7-Eleven to spot sales trends and take advantage of consumer purchasing behavior more quickly than its competitors. It offers them a statistical advantage in what was a fairly saturated market for convenience stores that to this day helps reassert their market dominance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But 7-Eleven’s success in Asia may very well be a fortuitous coincidence, one engendered by geographical constraints and cultural attitudes. The convenience store model works largely in Asia because populations are so densely packed in urban settings there. Consumers in Asia are also accustomed to shopping at smaller vendor units who sell at smaller quantities, whereas their American counterparts tend to buy in bulk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It remains to be seen if 7-Eleven can overcome these barriers to achieve market penetration elsewhere, in light of its recent plans to rapidly expand in parts of the United States, such as Manhattan and Portland. The chain has already seen resistance &lt;a href=&quot;http://nymag.com/news/features/7-eleven-2012-5/&quot;&gt;from lovers of New York City bodegas&lt;/a&gt; threatened by its Slurpee slinging franchisees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/7-eleven_noodles.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;7-Eleven Noodles&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of its presence in the rest of the world, 7-Eleven is a commercial force to be reckoned with throughout most of Asia, and it’s unlikely that will change anytime soon. I get this funny feeling, walking around in the streets of Taiwan, and bumping into the inevitable convenience store lit by its iconic green logo, having to acknowledge this magical little store stuffed with an endless inventory of things to be a cultural fixture in the urban landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it a good or a bad thing? Only time can tell. For now, at half past three in the morning, I’m happy that I can simply walk half a block down the street to cure my late night munchies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://wikichen.as/blogger/why-7-eleven-is-everywhere-in-asia/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://wikichen.as/blogger/why-7-eleven-is-everywhere-in-asia/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Taiwan Eats: My Favorites</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a 3-part series on Taiwanese food culture: &lt;a href=&quot;/taiwan-eats-part-1/&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt; explores food you find on the streets, &lt;a href=&quot;/taiwan-eats-part-2/&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt; talks about family style eating, and &lt;a href=&quot;/taiwan-eats-part-3/&quot;&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt; highlights some of my favorite dishes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best part about going back to Taiwan was getting to eat some of the favorite things I ate growing up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Tofu&quot; src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/eats-part3-tofu.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Douhua (豆花) or tofu pudding is a Chinese dessert consisting of very soft tofu. Sometimes toppings like tapioca pearls are added for more flavoring. It’s a traditional Taiwanese dish and a refreshing treat on a hot day. Think pudding with a softer, soy twist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Almond Tofu&quot; src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/eats-part3-almondtofu.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almond tofu (杏仁豆腐) is very similar to tofu pudding in consistency, but it’s made with apricot kernels and as such has a very distinctive, savory taste. It’s a dessert usually served, as in the dish above, with toppings, such as red and green beans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Black Tea&quot; src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/eats-part3-blacktea.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being the birthplace of the popular tapioca drink (also known as boba) and a huge exporter in teas (accounting for about 20% of global production of oolongs), Taiwan has some of the best tea shops in the world. That means black tea that will blow your mind. It’s the perfect summer’s drink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Porridge&quot; src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/eats-part3-porridge.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I was a kid I’ve had an affinity for rice porridge. It’s also a very traditional Taiwanese breakfast item when coupled with a variety of side dishes and eggs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Condiments&quot; src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/eats-part3-condiments.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spiced bamboo shoots, pickled vegetables, and rousong (also called meat floss) are some of the side dishes we eat with porridge. The relative blandness of the porridge accompanied by the strong flavors of these processed sides make for an interesting and delicious palette.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Eggs&quot; src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/eats-part3-eggs.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different types of eggs are also part of the side dish selection, in particular century eggs and salted duck eggs. Both are preserved in special ways, but the tastes are wildly different. Century eggs have dark green yolks and brown, translucent whites, with a creamy consistency and smell like ammonia, while salted eggs have a briny texture due to the salt curing process, with a firm yolk that’s bright orange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Sausage&quot; src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/eats-part3-sausage.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taiwanese sausages are miles ahead of American ones in the taste department. Due to the emulsification process of the fat and meat, Taiwanese sausages generally contain more sugar and thus are sweeter in taste. They’re aptly called xiangchang (香腸), which translates to fragrant sausage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Tapioca Dessert&quot; src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/eats-part3-tapioca.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite possibly my favorite dessert of all time, tapioca is traditionally used in desserts much like this one, instead of the boba balls you typically see in drinks. The small tapioca pearls are combined with grass jelly and other equally delectable jelly substances in a soup-like concoction, and the result is life-alteringly amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you enjoyed this gastronomic tour of Taiwan. What I’ve shown, however, only scratches the surface of Taiwanese cuisine. If you’re interested in learning more, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taiwanese_cuisine&quot;&gt;Wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt; goes into more detail about the customs and nuances of Taiwanese food. I also &lt;a href=&quot;/photowalking-through-a-taiwanese-night-market/&quot;&gt;take a photowalk through a Taiwanese night market&lt;/a&gt; in another post, which is arguably the best way to experience the amazing culinary side of Taiwan.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://wikichen.as/foodie/taiwan-eats-part-3/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://wikichen.as/foodie/taiwan-eats-part-3/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Taiwan Eats: Family Style</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a 3-part series on Taiwanese food culture: &lt;a href=&quot;/taiwan-eats-part-1/&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt; explores food you find on the streets, &lt;a href=&quot;/taiwan-eats-part-2/&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt; talks about family style eating, and &lt;a href=&quot;/taiwan-eats-part-3/&quot;&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt; highlights some of my favorite dishes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One noticeable part of American culture that baffled me when I first moved to the United States was how dishes or entrees weren’t shared between members of a party eating together. In most Chinese households, meals are often structured in a way such that entrees are placed in the middle of the table and everyone shares from the central array of food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This cultural dinner procedure makes for much better social dynamics during meals, because every member of the party is knowingly and actively sharing the same food, promoting a sense of togetherness and mutual engagement. It’s why most Chinese restaurants have circular tables, and sometimes ones with a rotating platform in the center to facilitate passing the dishes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sharing and eating around the same food makes for a much better social dining experience. For me, recounting meals with friends and family is enhanced by the fact that everyone was eating &lt;em&gt;together&lt;/em&gt;. The photos below were some of my favorite meals in Taiwan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Group Chicken Meal&quot; src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/eats-part2-chicken.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Family Style Lunch&quot; src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/eats-part2-familylunch.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Family Style Dinner&quot; src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/eats-part2-familydinner.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Pickled Intestines&quot; src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/eats-part2-intestines.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Seafood&quot; src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/eats-part2-seafood.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Fish Soup and Duck Tongue&quot; src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/eats-part2-soupduck.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Guava&quot; src=&quot;http://oasis.wikichen.com/writing/uploads/2013/08/eats-part2-guava.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside: I just want to give a shoutout to guava, one of my favorite fruits whose absolute deliciousness seems not to have caught on across the Pacific. My favorite way of eating guava is to cut out the seedy portion and dab the slices in some plum powder. So good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continue to &lt;a href=&quot;/taiwan-eats-part-3/&quot;&gt;Part 3 of this foodie series&lt;/a&gt;, where we check out some of my favorite Taiwanese foods.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://wikichen.as/foodie/taiwan-eats-part-2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://wikichen.as/foodie/taiwan-eats-part-2/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>